when 3.8 27 billion is out. Okay, this
is the model that I was waiting for.
I've been using the previous version,
the 3.6 27 billion for quite a while and
it's become my daily driver. I do 80% of
the work with that model. I like it a
lot. I bought a new computer just to run
that model. I now run it on the 5090 and
it's performing amazing. So you can
imagine how much I was waiting for this
new version and unfortunately I have
mixed feeling about it. Now I want to
explain because this is really
important. There is something extremely
important to understand but also I have
an insane good news about this model.
This is what Quen released and this is
the reason why a lot of people are
comparing it to Obus 4.6. I personally
I'm not much interested in this model.
I'm more interested to understand what
I'm gaining from what I had before to
what I can run today. And I can see that
in some scenario the gap is not that
big. But other scenarios like here
aentic coding the gap is huge from 13.3
to 42.2 is massive and software
engineering from 49.3 to 79. This is
another massive step forward on frontier
agenting task from 10.6 to 20. This is
100% improvement. The gap sometimes are
pretty noticeable. So why I felt this
mixed feeling when I I tested myself
because I tested the Quen 3.6 27 billion
Q6 with the Quen 3.8 8 27 billion Q5. In
my test bug hunting, the Q6 found one
more bug than the Q5, even though the Q5
was the newer version. So, I stopped the
test and I said, "Okay, this is uh this
is disappointing first, but let's
compare them with the same
quantization." So, I also installed the
Quen 3.8 to 27 billion Q6. then I could
see the difference, but the difference
was still not that big as much as I was
hoping for. So there is probably, it's
hard to tell, but let's say a 30%
improvement, which is noticeable, but
not another level. So I was expecting
much more. This is because Luna itself
could do such a great job when improving
reasoning. So here is GPT 5.6 Luna, no
reasoning 27. When we start increase
reasoning go to 34 then 39
then
47 and then GP 5.6 Luna max 52. The jump
is insane is more than double the
capability.
So let's look at when 3.6 27 billion no
reasoning 31. When does reasoning go to
38? I was expecting okay the new model
is going to be better as a model but
plus then going to increase reasoning so
it should push us towards this kind of
level we are probably in the 40 but I
was hoping to get actually up to in the
50s that is reality considering that
when no reasoning 31 and Luna no
reasoning is 27 so potentially we could
have done much more than 50 and reach
you know this kind of a level, the
DeepSc version 4 Pro, that would be
amazing. The GLM 5.2 Max. Okay, that
would be an amazing achievement, but we
didn't. So, probably I was expecting too
much. But let me tell you the good news
here. The good news is this model is
capable. But
intelligence is not just about the model
is the harness around it. Before I
explain why I'm talking about harness
now because I found the killer combo
between this model and a harness. Until
now I was using Hermes and open code.
And while Hermes I find it that is a
fantastic system
recently when they start pushing their
own subscription I felt like yeah that
is not cool anymore I felt like a client
I'm a guest within their system and this
is the reason why I'm building with my
community Resonant OS so we can co-own
it and it's ours. The moment they
started pushing that subscription, the
moment that people are starting asking
me is do I need to subscribe to use
Hermes, I could see that Hermes just
took the wrong path. Okay. And therefore
I was already open with the idea I need
to look to something different with
Rontos. I was thinking okay for us
everything needs to be an adon. Okay,
all the elements need to be possible for
the community to add to this system. So
they can customize, they can change it.
They can replace part, they can replace
the memory, they can replace the main
agent, they can replace all those parts,
but at least we have a system that we
can work together and build it and
customize together. So at one point I
came across randomly to this new harness
that came out recently. I think less
than a week ago, DeepS released Deepseek
harness. Now, I believe that this is the
best combo for Quen 3.8 27 billion. I
started using this harness. I'm going to
explain a little bit even though I will
probably need to do a dedicated video to
this harness because it does something
that no other harnesses do. What
happened? I start using it together with
this uh new version of Quen and
everything I wanted to build so far it
built. So in the past I used to use Quen
3.6 27 billion let's say 80% of the
time. Sometimes it would find a problem
that was not solvable. I had to change
model and use one of those frontier
model. Now with this deepseek harness
and the new 3.8 8 27 billion. I never
had a problem to swap to a different
model. So what is happening here? When I
went to this website, I read everything
is a plug-in. So in my world, everything
is an addon. For them, everything is a
plug-in. It resonated and say, I need to
look into this thing. I was coming from
uh not totally sure about Hermes
anymore. We are still building with our
community Reserant OS. I see this that
says everything is a plug-in total
alignment. I installed it. Actually, I
didn't even install. I asked Hermes to
install it for me and configure it with
the new model. And it's amazing. So now
this is how it looks like. Okay. And I
can't show you while it's running
because while it's running I can't
record the screen because memory
management of the file format that I'm
uh recording. What I can tell you here
is that it's just amazing. It's not a
finished product. Okay. Okay. So they
call it developer preview. So it's not
finished. It's there is a lot of things
maybe are missing. Things are not
perfect. So sometimes it doesn't do
compaction in the right moment and
therefore it's a kind of crash the
system nothing serious because you just
say resume working and it start working
without any problems but nevertheless
it's still a preview but what they did
they change how the contest window is
managed. What is happening here it's
unbelievable.
There is a lot of new elements inside.
So it takes track of everything that has
been done and require for whatever
system that they use less context
window. I can't explain because it's
confusing to me. So I need to read
understand it better. But what I know
it's these 131,000 tokens that I have
available for this model on my 5090.
They just last longer. The compaction is
so much more solid. And this system is
been chatting for so long, building for
so long. That is incredible. So if you I
don't know if you can see, but here it
had an input of 38 million tokens,
still going strong. What did I build
with this? I built this the agumentor.
This is my agent. Okay, this is how I
call my agent. This is part of Resonant
OS is also included in resonant. Now I
built the agumental that is powered by
this deepseek harness. What it does is
uh it takes total control of the browser
and and it just go around and click and
do things for me. So what I ask here was
to check out of my latest videos to see
the comment and suggest a few videos
idea. So that was a way to send these
agents into the browser. click around
and grab information.
So, here is what came out. It checked
four, five different videos. He saw some
of the comments and then come out with
some ideas. Now, it doesn't matter the
ideas because it's honestly I don't from
what I see maybe are valuable, maybe
not, but doesn't matter because it
didn't have the instruction of what is
this channel is about and so on. So, at
the moment it doesn't have much context.
It just went there and grabbed
information. But what is important is
what was capable of doing. I built the
whole thing with this Quen 3.8.
It works completely fine. Yeah, there is
a little things that need to be
improved. And the most important part, I
never had the need to use a bigger
model. Something that always happened
before when was doing something as
complex at this kind of tasks. So, we
have another deepseek moment, but this
time the deepseek moment is not on the
model, is on the harness and is done by
deepseek. Now, I'm extremely curious to
see what this harness can do even with a
more powerful model. If you've been
following this channel, you know that
I'm really pro local AI and so on. um
for the AI sovereignty meaning you need
to own the hardware and the
infrastructure so you can trust and
control everything. This is the journey
but it's not first of it's not for
everybody but also is it's a journey is
not a non-off what I can see with this
deepseek harness that the journey is
getting better and better because now we
have this harness that has MIT license
meaning you can use it in your project
you can use it yourself implement change
it do whatever and use for commercial so
what I'm suggesting here if you are
watching this video probably it's
because you have access to this model.
But even if you don't try this uh DeepS
harness, if you're one of those lucky
people that own a two DJX Spark or
equivalent, try DeepSk version 4 flash
because can run on two of them with this
harness that probably they could work
amazingly together. I'm at moment after
a few months of of struggling with this
AI. I'm excited again. I think it's a
similar moment of when open claw came
out which was called
clawbot I think. Can't even remember
anymore.
So when it came out it just was a
massive push forward because everybody
finally had this agent that can do a lot
take control of your computer work for
you and so on. So now I think what
DeepSync did with their harness is a
similar jump
allows this model to do so much more
which is incredible. I will need to test
this for longer. Of course I can't say
you know that is the final solution but
at moment this is what I feel. I feel
like I never needed a more powerful
model than this when I use this harness.
something that I can't say the same with
Hermes or open code. I think it's a
killer combo. I need to understand this
deepseek harness even more. At Monte is
not fully finished the way it works.
It's uh surprisingly well. So, if I were
you, first of all, go to this dsec.com
harness and uh and read it through. Like
I said, I will do a new video, but
they're definitely managing the things
differently. And now what is possible to
achieve with this harness and the quen
3.8 27 billion is impressive. This is
going to be my new way of working for
now on I will need to migrate and learn
how to do it from Hermes to this model.
Again the good thing that is happening
that is I basically already built this
agent. This agent the augmentor. This
can be a an addon for resonant OS and
again shows the importance of working in
addons or plugins like they call it
because now it's easy to implement new
things. And what I can't even believe is
that I build this 100% with my local AI,
not needing a more powerful system.
Everything that I ask to do has been
done, not getting lost and so on. One
thing that I want to say about DeepS
harness connected together with this
quen 3.8 to 27 billion is they use a lot
of token. Okay, let's use a lot of
toads. But
the result is there. We know that the
direction was increase the thinking time
and you you will perform better. Here is
happening and is incredible. Let's look
at the what kind of hardware you need to
run this model. In theory, according to
Quen, you can run it on 12 GB of RAM.
Ideally, a 48 GB of RAM. And I would
agree on the 48 GB of RAM because what
you gain is actually a larger contest
window. I have the 32 GB of RAM. Okay. A
Q6
and 25 GB. And look, I only lose 0.2%
from the Q8. So the compromise is pretty
acceptable. With the Q5, you lose a
little bit. You lose 1.4.
At 1.4, for you say okay that is not
much and I mean from this one but you
lose a 1.6 six from the top is still not
that much, but from my benchmark that I
run earlier,
the bug hunting, the Q6 could find one
more bug than the Q5.
So, it is a little bit, you know,
annoying this thing. So, here's my
suggestion. If you're looking for a
bigger contest window, Q5 is fine. If
you need to do some specific work that
is more advanced, of course, you need to
move into the Q6. Ideally,
if you have the 32 GB of RAM, I'm
explaining this because it's important
to understand what are the limits. When
you go into the 16 GB of RAM, you start
to lose quite a bit. At 12 GB of RAM,
you lose a lot.
So while I never tried these two models,
okay, I never tried them. I can't say
how much you're losing from the model.
This is something that you need to test
yourself. But knowing that the minimum
minimum requirement is 12, ideally you
want to be in the 24, 32, 48 if you can
do it. So now another elements you need
to consider is the side of the memory
that is required to run this model. But
the speed at which the model runs is
connected to the bandwidth. So I just
listed here I use these perplexes to
this research on the 32 GB of RAM and 24
GB of RAM. So here for the 32 GB of RAM
the best one is the 5090. Okay. This has
a bandwidth that is insane. 1,792
GB per second. That means the this model
is working at around 100 110 token per
second on my hardware. It's doing
insanely well. So when you go on this
one, you can see that the AMD is doing
640. This is almost a third of the
speed. So you have an idea of what you
can expect. Now on the 24 GB of VRAM, we
have a different kind of opportunity.
000 gigabyte per second which is pretty
good. 3090 is the same. The good thing
with 1390 that you can find them
secondhand much cheaper. This is the 390
idle. So the 39 normal 3090 is here
which is basically not not a big of a
difference. Okay, it doesn't really
matter. But from AMD, we have this card
which is still in commerce that you can
buy and it's not as expensive as those
1490 and the speed is almost there. Now
those are 24 GB of RAM. So if I were in
Europe and if you can afford I mean two
of these together they give you 48 GB of
RAM which again give us this 48 GB of
RAM. I would not run the Q8. I would go
for the Q6 but with a much bigger
contest window. Have in mind that you on
my 32 GB of RAM I can have 131,000 token
contest window with 48. You probably I
guess you could have the the total 260
something context window which is a nice
plus. Remember Q8 is going to run slower
than the Q6. The Q6 slower than Q5 and
so on. bandwidth. It is something to
consider at the moment. If you want to
buy new, this is really good. If you're
looking for secondhand, this is pretty
good. One more thing, this model can run
on a DGX Spark and it runs depending on
the quantization at around 20 30 to per
second. At 30 to per second, in reality,
you have a system that works, is usable,
and I will probably run it and test it
on my GX10. This is the Asus version of
the DJX Spark. It's 128 GB of RAM, so I
can run it with really large context
window with multiple instances. So, that
would be the advantage. Anyway, that is
what I wanted to share for today. To
recap, a model that is not as good as I
wanted. It didn't do the jump that I was
expecting and wanting. Probably we're
going to see it when they release the
version four of it. But combining this
with Deep Seek harness, I saw something
that I never saw before. It's early days
to say, but so far in the last 24 hours,
I use it a lot. And I never felt I
needed to use a bigger model. Never
once. [clears throat]
That make me think that things are
changing and local AI is gaining more
and more value every single day. If
you're interested in this kind of
content and you want to join our
community, first like and subscribe. In
the description, you find the link to
our discord channel and there is a deep
dive article. I will go deeper in
everything that I talk inside this uh
video. I will add all the links that I
discuss over here and if possible I will
see how it goes. But I might also share
this augumentor powered by DS DSH. This
is an extension for the browser and by
adding it you can have this sidecar
which honestly is amazing. It is
actually amazing. I say if I can because
what is missing before I can share it is
a way for you to add your own model. At
the moment there's no a configuration
system where you can add your API or
logger model or something. Even though
through the code you could be able to
ask to your agents to add the model. I
want to make it through the interface so
everybody can just add their you know
details and run it locally or for any
other cloud provider. So if I can manage
to do this in time, I will link inside
the Substack article the code for this
um agent. If not, will be shared in the
in the near future. Thanks for staying
until the end. Again, like and
subscribe, watch the next video, join
the Discord, and uh ciao.